Well, good morning, Canvas.
Thanks so much for joining us.
A miracle just happened.
I told the tech team, if I get from my guitar to the preaching table without tripping over
a cord or ripping a cord out, then we are in really good shape.
And we did it.
We're here.
We made it.
If you don't know me yet, my name is Ryan.
I'm going to have the privilege of being one of the pastors here, and I'm so glad that
you have joined us this morning, this Sunday after Thanksgiving.
And I happen to always do this whenever we're here around the holiday, which I call holiday
Sunday.
I tell you that if you are here on a holiday Sunday, you get extra points in heaven.
So receive that blessing this morning.
If you're online, I will give you half extra points in heaven.
You receive half extra points in heaven in the name of the Father, the Son, and the Holy
Spirit.
I'm just kidding.
But maybe.
Who knows?
Hey, this morning we are kind of wrapping up a series that happened inadvertently.
So we had planned on doing this series through the book of Daniel, which hopefully you guys
remember.
You didn't forget everything that we talked about through the series of Daniel.
And then we had like three to four weeks in between with a baptism before Christmas series.
And we were kind of just going to do a little standalone thing, you know, here or there, pick
what we felt like the Lord was leading us to.
And that's kind of what we did.
But what ultimately happened through that, which is really cool, is the Holy Spirit kind of
like work in individuals in the way that we were kind of forming our individual messages.
And they kind of formed this little mini series.
I like to organize things.
I like to name things.
I'm just an administrative guy.
I name things.
I put labels on things.
It makes me happy.
And so I kind of labeled this little mini series Peaks and Valleys because we've really been
talking about the highs and lows of the Christian faith.
We talked about kind of at the beginning, Brandon talked about self-reflection and identifying
where we're at in our relationship with God and working through that.
That was kind of like a, let's just be honest with where we're at with God.
And then we celebrated baptism, right, which is like the highest of highs when it comes to
the Christian church and faith.
And then lastly, Pastor Joel, I thought, did an incredible job talking about kind of the
highs and the lows, right?
Like sometimes in the lowest of lows, it's hard for us to see something beyond that.
But then he gave us this beautiful message of hope for the future.
And at the end, he quoted an Old Testament prophet by the name of Habakkuk.
And he said, when he says Habakkuk, it makes me feel like he's cussing in the pulpit, which
is kind of fun for a pastor because, you know, we don't get to cuss in the pulpit.
And sometimes it just feels good to do it.
So it's funny, as he said that, I had already kind of felt the Lord stirring in my heart
to bring a message on the book of Habakkuk to kind of close out this little mini-series
on peaks and valleys.
Habakkuk happens to be one of my favorite books of the Bible, probably my favorite book in the
Old Testament.
And no, I don't just say that to get brownie points because I went to Bible college because
a lot of you didn't even know that Habakkuk was a book in the Bible.
And so oftentimes when I tell people Habakkuk's my favorite book in the Old Testament, they're
like, wow, brag much?
Like, I didn't even know that was a book of the Bible.
But I think hopefully by the end of this message, you will kind of have an affection towards
this book because I think it's really helpful and really practical in some really important
ways.
And so, yes, we are going to cover an entire book of the Bible this morning, but don't
worry.
It is short.
We will not go long.
I promise.
And so this probably isn't like the typical Sunday after Thanksgiving message because Habakkuk
is a hard book about a guy who's struggling with God in some really difficult seasons in
his life.
And I kind of, I grew up in middle-class white church.
And what we tend to do in middle-class white church is we tend to put our smiles on and pretend
like everything is okay, even when we're struggling.
And so what we've tried to do at Canvas is we've tried to create space where if you're
happy, like, by all means, like, be happy.
Like, the Lord has blessed a lot of us in a lot of different ways.
But I also want to acknowledge people's pain and realize that all of us aren't always going
to be in that place of happiness and joy.
And you shouldn't have to feel like you have to put your fake face on and pretend at church.
And the reality is this Thanksgiving was probably hard for a lot of us.
There were probably empty seats at the table that haven't been empty before for probably
difficult seasons.
And yes, we fought through that and we found joy and we celebrated in the midst of that.
But the reality is I think it's important to name that and be honest with each other and
with God about that.
And I think there's no better place to kind of hone in that message than through the book
of Habakkuk, which we'll see here in just a minute.
So let me pray and then we'll kind of dive into where we're headed this morning.
God, we love you.
We thank you so much for the community of faith that we call the church, for brothers and sisters
in Christ who can come around us and lock arms with us when we're struggling and encourage
us and give us hope for a future.
God, we thank you for all the things that you've been doing in our lives over the past couple
weeks and months.
And I pray as we enter into this season of Advent, of expectation, that we would really
look to you, that we wouldn't just go through the motions and do the things that we've always
done, that we wouldn't just go to the Advent calendar and count off the days till Christmas.
But we'd be intentional to seek you and to see your face in the midst of this season.
God, show us yourself through your word, through worship, through fellowship today.
Holy Spirit, speak to us individually what we need to hear.
In Jesus' name I pray.
Amen.
Well, if you want to follow along, I'd love to have you turn to that book, Habakkuk.
It is one of the last books in the Old Testament.
And so the easiest way I tell people to find it is if you turn to the first book of the
New Testament.
If you turn to Matthew, take a left a couple pages over, you should find it.
It's only two to three pages in your Bible, so it might be hard to find.
But as you're turning there, I'd love to have us kind of do a thought exercise on a moment
that I'm sure most of us have experienced before.
How many of you have ever experienced where you were watching a movie, an emotional movie,
an in-depth movie, and somebody from your family happens to walk in the room towards the end
of the movie, and they do the thing that none of us want them to do?
They begin to ask you questions because they don't understand the plot of the movie.
Anybody ever been there or done that?
You ever, spouses, siblings walk in and they, you're like into this movie, right?
Like you're following along with a plot line, like it's got you, the director has done such
a good job.
You're in the movie, and the last thing you want to do is rehash all of the details that
have got you up to this point.
But we've all been there.
We've all experienced that before.
And that's frustrating because oftentimes movies are structured in such a way that if you walk
in towards the end, you really won't understand and won't get it if you don't have the context
of the rest of the story.
And really, that's how the book of Habakkuk is laid out.
The most powerful and prophetic and poetic message comes at the very last part of the book.
And it's often quoted and put on coffee mugs.
Christians are really good at putting things on coffee mugs without context.
It's like a, it's a, it's a, it's a pastime of ours.
And so this is how the book of Habakkuk ends with this incredibly poetic passage in, in
chapter three, verse 17, the, the prophet Habakkuk says, even though the fig tree has no
blossoms and there are no grapes on the vine, even though the olive crop fails and the fields
lie empty and barren, even if the flocks die in the fields and the cattle barns are empty, yet I will
rejoice in the Lord.
I will be joyful in the God of my salvation.
The sovereign Lord is my strength.
He makes me as sure-footed as the deer able to tread upon the heights.
And so we might be tempted to walk into the end of the story where Habakkuk saying, if everything
goes wrong, if there's no crops in the field, no, no meat in the barn, like if, if we have
nothing, no provision, nothing, I'm going to rejoice in the Lord.
And again, if you're, if you're cynical like me at all, you might find yourself being like,
okay, that's really easy for you to say.
Like you're a prophet of God.
You've heard specifically from God.
And so it might be really easy for you to kind of put your face on and say, yeah, I'm going
to rejoice in the Lord, even though everything goes wrong, even though nothing looks like I
thought it was supposed to look like.
It might be easy for you to say that, but for me, I don't know if I can get there.
But the reality is just like those dramatic movies that, that kind of suck us in and don't
make sense without the rest of the story.
The book of Habakkuk, the end of Habakkuk, where he says, yet I will rejoice in the Lord.
No, no matter what might happen, no matter what difficult circumstances might come my way,
I'm going to rejoice in the Lord.
That passage doesn't come without context.
As a matter of fact, the, the, the whole book of Habakkuk is him wrestling with God and
being angry and frustrated and questioning God.
Like, how can you do this?
How can you let these things happen?
And none of this makes sense to me.
And so just like the endings of these emotional movies make little sense without context, the
end of Habakkuk makes little sense without understanding his process to how he got there.
And so I've titled my message this morning, The Yet Process.
I don't often title messages.
It's not a thing that I do, but I think this title really helps us kind of understand what's
happening in the book of Habakkuk.
And that is that he, it takes him three chapters.
It takes him the entire book in this process to get to the point where he can say, yet I will
rejoice in the Lord.
See, I think for those of us that grew up in the church, some of us were, were just told
that we had to have the peace that passes understanding.
And no matter what difficult circumstances, don't question, don't ask, don't wrestle, don't
struggle.
Just put your fake face on and pretend like everything is okay.
And that's not what the Scripture invites us to do.
The Scripture actually invites us to bring our pain, our difficulty, our questions to God
and say, God, I don't get it.
I don't understand your purposes or your plan here.
It seems like you're not fulfilling the promises that you told me you were going to fulfill.
Can you please help me understand?
And that's what we see in Habakkuk.
The book's broken up into two complaints and two responses.
Habakkuk comes to God with questions and frustrations and says, help me understand.
Help me see how this all works out.
And, and fortunately for us in the Scriptures, God responds to Habakkuk.
But I don't want us to set up that as like a false paradigm that God always is going to
respond to us immediately because sometimes the response is silence.
But fortunately for us, we, we get God responding back to Habakkuk.
And then because of this dialogue, because of this process, eventually, we don't know how long it took, could take, could take months or even years.
Eventually, Habakkuk gets to a point where he can say, yet I will rejoice in the Lord.
I will be joyful no matter what my circumstances might face.
And so my hope and my prayer throughout this message is that we would learn from Habakkuk's process.
And that no matter what our circumstances are, some of us are in here like, Ryan, seriously, another downer message.
Let's like, let's move on, get past it.
Let's get to Christmas and let's be happy.
So maybe some of you are like, you've got some really good circumstances in your life and you've got a lot of things to be joyful about.
Hopefully you can say like, man, even if all of this stuff is worth, still I'm going to put my hope and my faith in Jesus for eternal blessings because these temporary blessings might pass.
But maybe you're in here and you're struggling.
And my hope and my prayer is at the end of this, that you'll learn this process that you can engage with God in to get to a point.
Where you can say, yet I will rejoice in the Lord.
I will be joyful in the God of my salvation.
So he starts, chapter 1, verse 1.
It says, this is the message that the prophet Habakkuk received in a vision.
He starts, how long, O Lord, must I call for help, but you do not listen.
That tune is a lot different than, even though the fig trees have no blossom, I'm going to rejoice.
Right?
He says, how dare you?
God, like I'm crying out for help, but you're not listening.
Violence is everywhere.
I cry, but you do not come to save.
Must I forever see these evil deeds?
Why must I wash all this misery?
Wherever I look, I see destruction and violence.
I'm surrounded by people who love to argue and fight.
If you're a mom of toddlers in here, you probably know exactly what he's talking about.
If you're on social media, you probably know what he's talking about.
I'm surrounded by people who love to argue and fight.
He says, the law has become paralyzed.
There's no justice in the courts.
The wicked far outnumber the righteous so that justice has become perverted.
So Habakkuk comes to God with this complaint.
And he says, how long will you let injustice go unpunished?
How long are you going to allow your people to rebel against you and to do whatever they want, however they want?
How long are you going to let this go on?
And I love that he doesn't really give us what most typical prophets in the Old Testament give us.
Most typical prophets give us like an introduction to who they are and when they're prophesying.
Like, so-and-so was the prophet during these days, and this person was the king.
Habakkuk just gets right to it.
God, how long are you going to let this go on?
And I think it's cool that we don't have that context because I think what it subtly communicates to the reader is don't worry about, like, don't compare your circumstances to other people's circumstances.
Like, if you've got a frustration, a difficulty, a complaint with God, like, just bring it directly to God.
It doesn't necessarily matter what the context is in Habakkuk's day.
The reality is he's got a complaint against God, and he's going to bring it to God.
Oftentimes, I think if we're honest, when we have difficulties, when we have frustrations, when we have complaints, rather than taking it directly to God, we look around at other people's circumstances.
And we compare our circumstances to their circumstances, and it keeps us.
It's like a tactic of the enemy to keep us from going directly to God.
Rather than going directly to God with our questions and our concerns and our frustrations, we tend to sit back and to play the comparison game and to say, well, man, it must be nice for them.
They don't have to deal with this.
And I think with Habakkuk not giving us context for his issues, it just reminds us that the proper response to pain is not to compare ourselves to other people's pain, but to bring our pain to God.
I heard the great theologian, this is not in my notes, the great theologian Joe Rogan say yesterday that the most painful thing that happened to you is the most painful thing that happened to you.
Even if you're in here and you've had terrible trauma and difficulty and pain, that's your experience.
Some of you have had a really easy life, and maybe you've only had minor difficulties, but that's still very painful to you because your context is things are okay, things are good.
And so wherever you might find yourself on the pain cycle, you shouldn't compare yourself to others and be like, well, I don't have it as bad as them, so I shouldn't complain.
No, if you're experiencing pain, bring that pain to God, no matter what it might look like.
So if you find yourself in a situation where you don't understand and things seem unjust, it's okay to be sad or angry, but let's bring those emotions to God.
That's what the deconstruction series is all about, right?
We said it's okay.
Like, no question is off limits if you take that question to God.
But if you're going to sit back and complain and argue and not be honest with God, then that's a problem.
We tend to make accusations about God without taking them to God.
And so Habakkuk just skips that step, and he goes directly to God.
He says, how long are you going to let an injustice reign?
And God responds in verse 5, awesomely, like usual.
It says, the Lord responds, look around at the nations.
Look and be amazed, for I am about to do something in your day, something that you wouldn't believe even if someone told you about it.
So at this point, if you're Habakkuk, you're like, sweet.
My God is going to listen to my complaint.
If he's going to do something about it, if you're like me, you might even begin to be quoting Scripture.
In your mind right now, like that passage that says, like, God is able to do far exceedingly abundantly more than we could ever ask or imagine.
Habakkuk's probably sitting back like, God is about to do something awesome in my day.
But that's not what he says next.
He says, I am going to raise up the Babylonians, a cruel and violent people.
They will march across the world and conquer other lands.
They are notorious for their cruelty and they do whatever they like.
Their horses are swifter than cheetahs and fiercer than wolves at dusk.
Their charioteers charge from far away like eagles.
They swoop down to devour their prey.
They come all bent on violence.
Hordes advance like a desert wind, sweeping captives ahead of them like sand.
And verse 11 says, they sweep past like the wind and are gone, but they are deeply guilty for their own strength is their God.
So God responds to Habakkuk's complaint, how are you going to let injustice reign in our day?
And God says, don't worry, I have a plan.
I am going to raise up the Babylonians.
I'm going to raise up this cruel and wicked nation and I'm going to allow them to execute judgment on you.
I'm going to let them execute judgment on the injustice that's happening in our day.
And if we're honest, something about this response doesn't sit well with us.
How can God let unjust people execute his judgment?
How can he let a worse nation execute judgment on a less worse nation?
And the reality is, when we think about how God interacts with us in our day,
our judgment around justice is often based on us being the center of the story of humanity.
Like America in 2021 is the center of God's eternal plan.
And so we look around and say, how can you be doing this?
How can you be letting this happen this way?
How can you let people get away with this?
And the reality is, God's plans are executed on an eternal timeline.
And so sometimes we get tempted to look just at like this one year, this one month, this one week in our life,
and we say, God, how can you let this happen?
If you're a good God, if you're faithful, how can you execute judgment in this way?
And the reality is, like, let me just give us a message that hopefully will let us breathe out this morning.
We're not the center of human history.
Like, I think America needs to get that through our thick brains.
Like, we think that we are the center of human history.
We think we're the greatest thing ever.
And the reality is, Jesus is the center of human history.
God's plan of redemption centers on the first and second coming of Jesus.
And so he executes his plans and his judgments on an eternal timeline.
And it's easy for us to get tempted, to get sucked into our day and age.
But I think God's trying to get Habakkuk to step outside of his little sphere of influence and say,
I'm, don't worry, I'm working, I'm moving, I'm going to bring about justice.
But it might not always look the way that you want it to look.
And Habakkuk responds the same way you or I would respond,
which is nice to know that a prophet of God is responding the same way that we would respond.
And he says in verse 12,
O Lord, my Holy One, surely you do not plan to wipe us out, not your people, not the nation of Israel,
because you're a pure God and you cannot stand the sight of evil.
Are you going to wink at the treachery of Babylon?
Should you be silent while the wicked swallow up people more righteous than they?
You hear what he's saying here?
He's saying, God, you can't take a more evil nation and execute judgment on an evil nation.
Like, he's building out this scale and he's saying, God, how can a holy God use a more unjust nation to judge a less unjust nation?
And then I love what he says at the beginning of chapter 2 in verse 1.
He brings this complaint to God and then he says, I'm going to climb up in my watchtower.
I'm going to stand at my guard post and I will wait to see what the Lord has to say and how he will answer my complaints.
See, we love to tell God how we would do things if we were him.
And oftentimes when we do that, we tend to judge on a curve that we design to make ourselves look better than we actually are.
Like, we love to come to God and say, God, if I were you, this is what I would do.
If I were you, this is how I would see things.
And what he says to God is, Israel, yes, we're bad.
We're an unjust nation.
We do bad and evil things.
But we're not near as evil as the Babylonians.
You can't use the Babylonians to execute your judgment on us.
How often do we do this?
Like, God, yeah, I know.
Like, I haven't been perfect.
I've made some mistakes.
But them?
You're going to let them get the promotion?
You're going to let them have the child?
You're going to let them reap that blessing or that benefit?
Like, I know I'm not perfect, but I'm better than them.
Nobody's ever done that before.
Nobody's ever said that before, right?
And that's where Habakkuk finds himself.
He says, this can't happen.
You can't be doing this this way.
This is not real justice.
You're a good God.
You can't let sin go unpunished.
But then I love that he brings his complaint to God.
And then he waits and listens for God's response.
He says, I will climb up on my watchtower.
I will stand in my guard post.
There I will wait to see what the Lord says and how he will answer my complaint.
Again, I told you at the beginning, this is one of my favorite books.
I've read this over and over and over again.
But this verse, chapter 2, verse 1, hit differently for me this year
because I picked up a new hobby recently.
I started hunting, which is weird for me because I'm a lover of all things furry and sweet.
But, you know, I decided.
There's a lot of reasons why.
But I decided to try and get into this thing.
And recently, like, I've been up in tree stands for the first time ever in my life.
And it kind of illustrates to me what Habakkuk's doing here.
He's saying, I'm going to go up.
I'm going to wait for the Lord to respond.
I'm going to watch.
I'm going to listen.
And when you're up in a tree stand, like, every little sound you hear, you're paying attention to.
You're observing.
You're putting this information into your brain because this information might help you get to the result that you want to get to.
And so I think as believers, if we're going to come to God with questions and struggles, we've got to learn to listen.
I feel like we are a generation of people that are bringing our frustrations and our complaints to God.
And we already have kind of a hypothetical answer in the back of our minds, and we're not letting him talk.
Like, we're never silent enough to actually let God speak.
We're filling our minds with information all the time.
And sometimes the best thing that we can do is come into our time of prayer with God and lay our requests, our complaints, our frustrations, our doubts, our fears, whatever it might be, lay it all before the Lord.
And then just sit back and listen.
Sit back and wait for God to respond.
See, I used to think that chapter 2, verse 1 was Habakkuk kind of arrogantly saying, like, I'm right, you're wrong, I'm going to sit here and wait.
But I think actually what he's communicating is, like, sometimes God speaks in all kinds of different ways.
And if we're not intentional to sit and listen, we might miss it all together.
We might bring our complaints, our frustrations, our questions to God, and he might speak back to us, but we might be so busy, so distracted that we're not actually hearing his response.
And so Habakkuk says, hey, I don't think you should work this way.
I don't think this is how all of this should go down, but I'm going to wait.
I'm going to listen.
I'm going to see what you might have to say about this.
And God graciously and lovingly responds to Habakkuk.
I think his response, too, is a two-part response.
First thing I want to point out is in verse 4.
He says back to Habakkuk, look at the proud.
They trust in themselves, and their lives are crooked.
He says, but the righteous will live by their faithfulness to God.
So Habakkuk's complaint is, how are you going to let injustice continue to happen?
And God's response is, I'm going to let the righteous, the righteous will be those who live by faith.
This verse is quoted so many times in the New Testament to draw out this idea of sanctification by faith, salvation, justification by faith in Christ.
And what God is saying to Habakkuk is, listen, injustice is injustice.
Rebellion against God is rebellion against God.
Whether it's Israel's rebellion against God or Babylonians' rebellion against God.
Like, you look at it, and you see one sin worse than the other sin.
But the reality is, sin before God is sin before God.
And all sin before God will be punished.
Some of it will be punished on the individual.
And others of it will be punished on the head of Jesus, who will come and live a perfect life.
And die a death that he does not deserve in our place for our sins.
See, what happens with Christ on the cross is judgment for sin is being executed for those who will live by faith.
Jesus, or God here is saying to Habakkuk, that rebellion against God is rebellion against God.
And God ultimately will execute his judgment on an eternal timeline.
And you might not understand it, and it might not be the way that you would do it if you were in charge.
But thank God you're not in charge.
Because God is a good God, a faithful God, a sovereign God who is going to execute his judgment on an eternal timeline.
And that might not always comfort us in the midst of our struggle and our difficulty.
And I don't think it necessarily comforts Habakkuk in the moment.
It's this process where he's wrestling and asking questions and listening to God.
And it's this process that our God invites us into when we struggle and when we have questions.
He invites us into this process where we wrestle with God and we wait and we listen.
We've got to be a people who learn to bring our requests to God and wait and listen.
So the first part of God's response is, hey, all injustice is going to be judged one day.
The only righteous people, the only people who won't be judged are those who live by faith.
Whether they be Gentile or Jew, Babylonian or whatever it might be.
Whoever places their faith and trust in me is the only people that will not be judged.
And then he goes on in verse 14.
And he says,
For as the waters fill the sea, the earth will be filled with an awareness of the glory of the Lord.
I think the second part of God's response to Habakkuk is, justice is executed on an eternal timeline.
He says, one day, there's going to come a day when my glory, my plan is going to so clearly fill the earth that it's going to be like the water covers the sea.
I just got back from the beach.
There's water everywhere.
Like, like, I got a saying to Habakkuk, one day, my plans are going to be so clear.
Like, right now, you look dimly, and you see part of my plans, and you can understand some of it.
But there is going to come a day when I am going to send myself in humanity.
That the word is going to become flesh and dwell among you.
And the plans, my plans, are going to be so clear that it's going to be as the water covers the sea.
See, God gives us this deeply poetic picture.
And remember, when we talked about prophecy in Daniel, we said that all prophecy points to Jesus.
And that the prophets, as they were writing these things, they were looking down this timeline, trying to figure out when it was that they were talking about.
And theologians have coined this term called already not yet.
And what this term means is that oftentimes prophecies about Jesus find partial fulfillment in his first coming, but ultimate fulfillment in his second coming.
And so I think this passage is both about the first coming and the second coming of Jesus.
That God's plans are ultimately going to be so clear to us that they fill the earth like the water covers the sea.
The best way I could think to illustrate this is high tide and low tide.
So I grew up, I love the beach.
How many beach people do I have?
You guys beach people?
A lot of beach people in here.
I grew up, I love the beach, but we always went Thanksgiving week.
That was like our tradition.
And it's pretty cold in South Carolina in November.
So I love the beach, but I didn't spend a lot of time by the water.
We did the forestry things.
Mini golf, lots of mini golf, all the mini golf.
But when I got married to Marissa, she lives close to the shore, about an hour from the shore.
And so her parents are like beach people through and through.
And like when I think about the beach, it's like we spend an hour by the water and then we do a ton of fun things.
Like her family, like they are by the water for like 12 hours a day, which I originally thought was really boring.
I was like, what are we doing here?
Like we're just going to sit and watch the water.
But they're like beach experts, and they taught me a couple of things.
They taught me to bring a chair, which I didn't used to do.
It's uncomfortable to sit in the sand for 12 hours.
Chairs help.
They taught me to bring books.
They taught me to bring like cornhole.
Like there's a lot of fun things you can do by the water.
But the coolest thing that they taught me is like they know the tides.
They know how the tides work.
And so they'll set up their kind of permanent camp waiting for high tide to come in.
But they'll take a chair or a towel down by low tide, and they'll kind of enjoy the water coming in.
But they know for a fact where the tide is going to end up because they've been there for so long.
And man, as I was thinking about this passage this week, what a beautiful illustration of the life of the believer.
Like the glory of the Lord is going to fill the earth like the water covers the sea.
And we have that low tide version of that right now.
We get to live on the other side of the first coming of Jesus.
We understand the blessings of Jesus in our life, and we can enjoy them and experience them in the moment.
But we better be setting up camp waiting for high tide.
We better be living our life with an eternal focus, listening to God,
and understanding that God's plans are executed on an eternal timeline.
Because let me be clear, the tide is coming in.
Jesus will return.
And if we set up camp and live for the temporary, we're going to miss out on so many of the blessings of God.
I remember so many times sitting back as the tide's coming in, where we set up camp.
And you see so many people scattering, people that aren't used to being at the beach, right?
Because they're like, oh, shoot, like where we set up is about to be covered with water.
And so they had to kind of ditch everything and find a new spot to set up.
This is kind of how the Christian life is.
Like we know one day the knowledge of the glory of the Lord is going to fill the earth as the water covers the sea.
So we live in anticipation for that day.
We don't get distracted by the temporary blessings of this earth.
We enjoy them.
We experience them in a good and a fresh way.
But we set up camp waiting for God's eternal plans to be set up.
This is God's response to Habakkuk.
Look, I know you don't get it.
I know it seems harsh.
I know it doesn't make sense to you where you're sitting.
But if you'll just trust me, if you'll place your faith in me and step back and wait,
I promise one day my plans are going to be made so clear to you.
So Habakkuk says, God, how long are you going to let injustice prosper?
How can you let a more unjust nation execute your judgment?
And ultimately, God responds, hey, just trust me.
I've got this thing.
It's going to work out.
And this is this process that Habakkuk is going through with God,
where he's bringing his questions and his frustrations and his concerns and his doubts and his fear to God.
And then God gives him the response.
And what we have in chapter 3 is a song.
Like Habakkuk sits down and writes a song.
And I think the reason that that's important to us is because oftentimes I think we maybe we feel guilty for not being able to feel the same way that God feels about things in the moment.
Like God responds to Habakkuk.
And I think we think we're supposed to just be like, okay, we got our answer.
Now everything, like let's just move on.
Everything's fine.
I can trust God now.
And the reality is the fact that Habakkuk sat down and wrote a song is I think that it was this process where he wasn't just overnight like, okay, God, I get it.
You're right.
I'm wrong.
I'm going to be happy now.
It's like, no, like I'm going to engage in my relationship with you.
I'm going to wrestle with my questions and my doubts and my concerns.
And it's going to be a process before I can get to this point where I say, yet I will rejoice in the Lord.
I will be joyful in the God of my salvation.
If you're here and you're wrestling with God, maybe you've gotten some answers and you're like, I don't like these answers.
Can we get some new answers?
Like can we like hit the reset button and get a new answer?
Maybe you're here and that's you.
And I just want you to find comfort in the fact that like you don't have to just snap your fingers and have everything be okay.
It's okay to wrestle with God, but do it in relationship with him.
Like be intentional to bring those things to him and do it in relationship with other people who have faith and trust in God,
who can encourage you and remind you of God's faithfulness.
And so Habakkuk, he sits down and he processes what he's heard from God and ultimately he responds in a song.
This is the longest intro to any message I've ever given because this is the main point that I hope we take home this morning.
That our faith to say yet in our present circumstances is based on God's eternal character, his past faithfulness, and his future promises.
Like if we examine Habakkuk's song, he gets to a point where he can say in the present moment where he got answers that he didn't like.
Things are happening in a way that he didn't want them to happen.
And he's able to say no matter what happens, if this judgment happens from Babylon, if everything goes away, if all of the fields are empty,
if all of the barns are empty, if we have no food, if we have no resources, yet I will rejoice.
He's able to say that.
Why?
I think because he reflects on God's character, on his past faithfulness, and on his future promise.
Look in verse 2 of chapter 3.
He says,
In your anger, remember mercy.
What Habakkuk is doing is he's quoting to God attributes of his character.
He's saying, God, you are a merciful God.
And so please, in your anger, choose to extend mercy to us.
God's eternal character is one of the reasons that Habakkuk is able to say, yeah, in the midst of his process.
And I'm a person that likes action.
So my tendency when I read this passage in verse 3 is like, I just wanted to focus on God's past faithfulness and his future promises.
But my wife, who is a worshiper, a meditator, a thinker, was like, no, it's not just about his actions.
It's also about his character.
Because sometimes all we have is his character.
Like, some of us, like, we have, we're not seeing his actions.
Like, if we look back at our past, if we think about our past, like, some of us don't have that.
And even if we don't have that, we have his character.
He's a good God.
He's a God of love, a God of mercy.
And God is the same yesterday, today, and forever.
God's character, his eternal character is good.
So our faith to say, in the present, is based on who he is, like, his nature, his very character.
But it's also, like, even if we don't have his past faithfulness in our situations, like, we have a history of God being faithful to the nation of Israel.
All the way up to the point where he sent Jesus.
And that's what Habakkuk does.
We don't have time to read through it.
But chapter 3, the first 12 verses of chapter 3, this song that Habakkuk writes, he meditates on what God did in the past, his past faithfulness.
He highlights how God delivered them out of Egypt through Moses.
He highlights how God led his people in the wilderness through a cloud of, a pillar of fire and a cloud of smoke.
He highlights how he parted the Red Sea in the Jordan River.
He highlights how God caused the sun to stand still for Joshua and the nation of Israel.
He's reflecting.
He's saying, God, I don't understand what you're doing right now in my moment, in my story, in my life, but I know you've been faithful in the past.
And because your eternal character is good, and because your track record of your faithfulness in the past is good, I'm going to cling to that.
I'm going to hold tightly to that.
And I'm going to believe in that.
And then I think he has in mind this future promise of Habakkuk 2, verse 14, that one day the glory of the Lord will fill the earth as the water covers the sea.
He says, like, your character's good.
You've been faithful in the past.
And you've made a promise for the future.
And so what happens in the present, it matters.
It makes me feel things.
But no matter what, I'm going to choose to say, yes, I will rejoice in the Lord.
I will be joyful in the God of my salvation.
Why?
Because I'm a person of faith.
And chapter 2, verse 4 says that the righteous will live by faith.
I'm going to choose to believe, God, you're good, you've been good, and you're going to be good, even if I don't see it here in the present.
Yet, I will rejoice in the Lord.
I love how Psalm 103, verse 10 puts it.
It says, God does not deal with us according to our sins, nor repay us according to our iniquities.
We're sinful.
We've broken God's law.
We deserve judgment.
And any grace we get outside of that judgment is more than we deserve.
And so even if the only answer to any of our questions, our frustrations, our concerns, our confusion, if the only answer we get when we come to God with our complaints is, I sent Jesus.
It's more than we deserve.
The only answer that we ever get to any of our questions is, Jesus is more than enough.
Our faith to say, yet, in our present circumstances is based on God's eternal character.
His past faith, once he sent Jesus the first time, and his future promises, we can cling right away to that fact.
Because because he sent Jesus the first time, we can have faith that he will send Jesus the second time.
And the glory of the Lord will fill the earth like the water covers the sea.
Let's be a people that cling tightly to this process of, like, wrestle with God in the midst of our struggles.
Like, I think there's one of two ways we can go when we experience pain.
The first way is, like, we can follow the example of Habakkuk, and we can do this process, this wrestling with God.
Choose to be faithful in the process.
But I think for so many of us, what we're tempted to do is have a faithless response.
And the way I see that playing out in my own life, I'm just going to call myself out in front of you guys,
and hopefully that will connect with you somewhere.
When I experience pain, when I'm not intentional to bring my pain to God in this process,
it ends up with resignation.
Where I'm angry, I have self-pity, depression.
I'm like, you know what, if this is my lot in life, this stinks.
And I don't want to deal with this right now.
And it also leads to loneliness, because nobody wants to be around a person like that.
Or maybe detachment, sometimes detachment.
Like, I'm like, if this is my reality, rather than bringing it to God and asking him questions and wrestling with him,
like, I'm just going to disconnect from my reality.
Maybe I find a substance that numbs the pain, or I binge watch, or I go on social media black holes daydreaming about a life that isn't the life that I'm actually in.
Or maybe it's none of those of you.
Maybe it's bravado.
Maybe you're a workaholic, and you generate this fake version of your life on social media for people to see,
because you don't want to deal with their actual life.
So you create this fake life that doesn't actually exist.
You try and manipulate and manufacture your own life.
These are faithless responses.
This is what we do in bringing our constraints to God.
I'm just going to help me understand.
I don't know where you're at this morning, but I think our goal as Christians is to get to a place where no matter what our present circumstances are,
we can say, yeah, I will rejoice in the Lord.
Hopefully, this is a message you can cling to around times like Thanksgiving, right?
Whether things are great or things are bad, you can still say, I will rejoice in the Lord.
I will be joyful in the God of my salvation.
Our faith is say yet in our present circumstances.
It's based on God's eternal character, who he is, his past faithfulness, what he's done, and his future promises, what he's going to do.
Let's be a people that learn to rejoice in the Lord no matter what our circumstances are because of who God is.
Because of what he's done, because of what we believe he's going to do with me.
Father, we thank you so much for real people with real lives like Habakkuk, who brought his complaints to you, his concerns to you, his questions to you,
who wrestled with you, who wrestled with you in doubt and frustration, and who heard a response from you that maybe he didn't necessarily like.
But he was a person of faith who was willing to trust you, no matter what the present circumstances look like, because of who you are, because of what you've done, and because of what you're going to do.
God, let us learn from his example.
Let us be real people with real lives.
Bring our struggles, our frustrations, our concerns, our questions, our doubts.
Bring them all to you.
Wrestle with what you might say in return.
And no matter what we hear, God, let us be a people who are able to say, yet I will rejoice in the Lord.
I will be joyful in the God of my salvation.
In Jesus' name I pray.
Amen.